Luca Tironi

Executive Engineer

Luca Tironi

Chodowieckistrasse 33 10405 Berlin, DE

(+49) 1578 4290922 luca.tironi@gmail.com

Skills

As an **Engineer** I write tested, readable and efficient code. I can work from the frontend layer (CSS, HTML, JS) to the depths of the backend (Ruby, Go, Microservices, API) and I have experience in DevOps as well (Docker, Cloud, Scaling, CI/CD).

As a **Technical Leader** I believe in the power of collaboration and problem solving. I have built both simple and complex systems from the ground up. I also led refactoring of legacy systems and structured methodologies to maintain and expand complex architectures.

As a **Manager** I strive to structure processes to help people to excel in creating and innovating. I have scaled engineering teams and supported the company to acquire and retain the best talents; organizing teams to be agile, independent and autonomous.

As an **Entrepreneur** I want to use my technical perspective together with my business experience to create new and compelling products.

Experience

DaWanda GmbH / Head of Engineering

May 2016 - Present (1 year, 5 months), Berlin

I managed 35+ engineers and structured them in product teams as fullstack units, in order to maintain and grow the DaWanda Marketplace Platform. I recruited new engineers to scale the Engineering Team. I developed a process together with the Engineering Leads to create a Technical Vision and grow a healthy Engineering Culture.

I represented the engineering perspective across the Company and contributed to strategic decisions according to the Technical Vision. I established a process to foster personal and professional development of engineers through timely and open feedback. I improved the Agile product management methodologies and introduced the OKRs to the Product Engineering Department.

DaWanda GmbH / Team Lead Software Development

November 2014 - April 2016 (1 year, 6 months), Berlin

I led the "Buyers" cross-functional team in expanding and improving the DaWanda Marketplace Platform. I contributed to the design and developed the first iterations of the DaWanda Mobile Apps.

As the Engineering Hiring Manager I improved the recruiting process and scaled the team consistently. I developed the foundation of the Backend API infrastructure that powered the mobile apps and the frontend.

UALA Srl / CTO & Co-Founder

June 2013 - October 2015 (2 years, 4 months), Milan

I co-founded and bootstrapped a new company in Milan called UALA: a marketplace for hundreds of hairstylists, beauty salons, SPAs and aesthetic centers all across Italy.

I developed the first iteration of the web marketplace, the administrative backoffice and the API for the tablet and mobile apps. I formed and trained the development team and built the infrastructure for the continuous delivery of the platform.

DaWanda GmbH / Frontend Developer

August 2013 - October 2014 (1 year, 2 months), Berlin

I joined as a frontend/fullstack developer in an agile international Product Development team. Together we built and maintained the biggest German Marketplace dedicated to Handmade and DIY products.

I helped the Product Development team to maintain and improve our multi-service platform, coding mainly in Ruby (on Rails), Javascript and other cutting-edge web technologies.

Fractalgarden Srl / Senior Developer, Product Designer

May 2011 - July 2013 (2 years, 3 months), Milan

Business Analysis and Development of new products. UX and Frontend Development with Ruby on Rails.

I curated the development of a IoT Photovoltaic Monitoring Platform dedicated to O&M companies and Solar Investments Funds. I was also responsible of the UX and interface design. I developed the iOS companion Mobile App for the platform and managed several refactorings of the platform's architecture and interface.

I developed and contributed to several other projects like custom E-Commerce Platforms and ERP Systems.

Università Bocconi / Expert Fellow

January 2010 - July 2010 (7 months), Milan

I collaborated in the design of the course "Managing in the 2.0 Landscape", part of the EMIT english course at Bocconi University (MSc, first year). I taught about topics such as social media tools' impacts in the work environment, web entrepreneurship and web application design and development.

I tutored 15 groups of students in their group-works: the development of a Business Plan in the Web 2.0 and Social Media environment.

SDA Bocconi School of Management / Senior Developer

September 2007 - March 2011 (3 years, 6 months), Milan

I designed and developed several business games and simulations, used in MBAs, masters and executives courses and other tools to support learning and teaching in education programs.

I researched the Web 2.0 phenomenon, designed and delivered lectures to students with in depth analysis of the growing importance of new media and their social, economic and technological impacts.

Freelancer / Web Developer

January 2006 - December 2007 (2 years), Bergamo

Designed and developed several websites and applications for italian companies and institutions, such as the Ministry of Public Education.

Education

Università degli Studi di Milano / BSc in Computer Science

2002 - 2006, Milan

Thesis: Realtime Terrain Rendering: optimization methods and techniques

The course of study was focused on general and graphic programming, game development, AI and communication through digital media.

Liceo Classico Statale Paolo Sarpi / High School Diploma

1997 - 2002, Bergamo

Humanistic studies, Philosophy, Art, Latin and Ancient Greek.

Personal Projects

lucatironi.net / Personal Blog

A site to share some of the knowledge and the code that I accumulated during my coding experience.

My Pretty Milano / iPhone & Android App

In 2011 I developed and launched an iPhone/Android app called "My Pretty Milano. The app featured cool venues and events in my city (Milano) with reviews and advices, collected by a small team of fashion victims and illustrated by a designer.

The apps have been downloaded more than 6600 times and had 3000+ active users to date.

Other

Languages: Fully proficient in English. Native Italian and basic German.

Hobbies: Cinema, Art, Sailing, DIY